A Guide to the Flagg Family Papers, 1776-1949
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Flagg Family Papers, 1776-1949
The Library of Virginia
45015
6 cubic feet (14 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Charles T. Edwards, Falls Church.
Biographical Information
Edmund Flagg was born in Chester, New Hampshire on 3 July 1786. He graduated from Dartmouth College in 1806, and was admitted to the bar in 1810, setting up practice in Wiscasset, Massachusetts (now Maine). A year later, Flagg went into partnership with Silas Lee (1760-1814), and was appointed Register of Probate in 1812. The following year, he married Harriet Payson. They had two children. In 1815, Flagg traveled to the West Indies to recuperate from poor health. He died in St. Croix on 14 December 1815.
His son, Edmund Flagg, was born in Wicasset on 24 November 1815. He graduated from Bowdoin College in 1835, and then moved to Louisville, Kentucky with his mother and sister. From 1836 to 1837, he taught school in St. Louis, and was admitted to the bar there. He then moved to Vicksburg, Mississippi, where he practiced law, and was editor of the Vicksburg Whig. From 1842 to 1843, he edited the Marietta Gazette in Marietta, Ohio, and then the St. Louis Gazette from 1844 to 1845. In 1850, Flagg was appointed United States consul for the port of Venice. He was superintendent of the Office of Statistics in the Department of State, and 1861, appointed head of the Copyright Library in the United States Patent Office. He retired in 1870, and moved to "Highland View" in Falls Church, Virginia. Flagg wrote numerous plays and books during his career, including The Far West: or, A Tour Beyond the Mountains (1838) and Venice: The City of the Sea From the Invasion of Napoleon in 1797 to the Capitulation of Radetzky in 1849 (1853). Edmund Flagg married Kate Adeline Gallaher (1839-1926) on 18 February 1862. They had four children. He died on 1 November 1890, and is buried in Oakwood Cemetery in Falls Church, Virginia.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1776-1949. of the Flagg family of Falls Church, Virginia, and Kentucky, Maine, Massachusetts, Missouri, Ohio, and Washington, D.C., namely Edmund Flagg (1786-1815) and his son Edmund Flagg (1815-1890). Includes accounts and receipts, agreements, clippings, composition books, correspondence, cyphering books, deeds, diaries, drafts of books and plays, estate papers, tax papers, records from the younger Flagg's work as editor of the Marietta Gazette, orations, school exercises, and scrapbooks.
There is a good deal of correspondence with John Henry (accused spy during the War of 1812), Samuel Livermore (legal writer), and Eloise Payne (sister of playwright John Howard Payne). The collection also includes manuscript drafts of Flagg's books and plays, including Sketches of a Traveller (1836) and The Far West: or a Tour Beyond the Mountains (1838), Ruy Blas: Marie of Suabia or The Flower of the Rhine (1845), Venice: The City of the Sea, From the Invasion by Napoleon in 1797 to the Capitulation to Radetzky, in 1849 (1853), and De Molai: The Last of the Military Grand Masters of the Order of the Templar Knights (1888). There are a large amount of clippings in the collection, many of which are contained in scrapbooks, that are reviews and notices of Flagg's work.
Contents List
- Abstracts of Title. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Account Book. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Account of Family Expenses, 1826-1828. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Account of Family Expenses, 1831-1833. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Accounts and Receipts, 1802-1886. (Box 1, Folder 5-38)
- Accounts and Receipts, n.d.. (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Accounts and Receipts (Loomis), Marietta. (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Accounts - Silas Payson/Mary Payson. (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Accounts - Silas Payson/Mary Payson. (Box 13)
- Address, 4 July 1843. (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Address, 8 December 1843. (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Advertisement - House for Rent. (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Agreements. (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Bank Protest, 1838. (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Barrett, Samuel H. and Henry C.. (Box 1, Folder 47-49)
- Bills of Sale. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Biographical Information. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Botanical Samples. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Catalogue of Books. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Certificate - Admission to the Bar, 1810. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Certificate - Ancient Egyptian Arabic Order Nobles Mystic Shrine, Acca Temple, 1897. (Box 13)
- Certificate - Domestic and Foreign Missionary Society, 1889. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Clippings. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Clippings - Catherine Howard, 1846. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Clippings - European War, 1866. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Clippings - Foreign News, April 1862. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Clippings - Mary Tudor, 1844. (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Clippings - Ruy Blas, 1845. (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Clippings - Venice, 1864. (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Cognovit Judgment, 1814. (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Commission - Register of Probate, 1811-1812. (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Commission - Justice of the Peace, 1814. (Box 13)
- Commonplace Book. (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Composition Books - Edmund Howard Flagg. (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
- Constitution - Washington Light Infantry. (Box 13)
- Jay Cooke & Co.. (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Correspondence, 1806-1880. (Box 3, Folder 1-41)
- Correspondence, 1881-1907. (Box 4, Folder 1-13)
- Correspondence, n.d.. (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Correspondence - John Henry, 1806-1810. (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Correspondence - Samuel Livermore, 1806-1808. (Box 4, Folder 16-17)
- Correspondence - Eloise Payne, 1808-1811. (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Court of Common Pleas, St. Louis, 1849. (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Cyphering Book. (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Cyphering Book of Silas Payson. (Box 4, Folder 21)
- De Molai: The Last of the Military Grand Masters of the Order of the Templar Knights (Drafts of Various Chapters). (Box 4, Folder 21a)
- Deeds. (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Diary, 1804-1806. (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Diary (Farm Book), 11 May 1871 - 31 July 1873. (Box 11)
- Diary - R. Chambers - Travel Down the Mississippi River, 1842-1843. (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Diary - Sydney Webster Flagg, 1886. (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Diary - Trip to England and France (4 vols.), 1849. (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Diploma - Spencerian Business College - Sydney Webster Flagg, 1893. (Map-case 2, Drawer 13)
- Election Ticket - St. Louis, Fifth Ward, 1856. (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Estate of Edmund Flagg. (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
- Estate of Edmund Flagg. (Box 13)
- Estate of Silas Lee. (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Estate of David Payson, Jr.. (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Exhibition Catalogue. (Box 5, Folder 10)
- The Far West: or, A Tour Beyond the Mountains - Manuscript Draft. (Box 5, Folder 11-15)
- Gallard, Isaac (Lee County, Iowa). (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Garfield, James A. - Assassination. (Box 13)
- Guardian's Bonds, 1814. (Box 5, Folder 17)
- House Resolution (Proposed), 1858. (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Income Tax. (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Index (unidentified). (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Insurance Policies. (Box 13)
- Inventory of Clothing and Bedding. (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Journal des Economistes Revue de la Science Economique et de la Statistique (Review of Report on the Commercial Relations of the U.S...), 1859. (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Leases. (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Ledger - School Notes (Greek History) - Edmund A. Flagg. (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Ledger - Spencerian Business College - Sydney Webster Flagg, 1892-1893. (Box 13)
- Legal Terms. (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Letter of Recommendation - John Wheelock. (Box 6, Folder 8)
- List of History Topics. (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Lists of Books Read. (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Lists of Law Books. (Box 13)
- Marietta Gazette - Accounts and Receipts. (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Marietta Gazette - Daybook, 1842. (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Marietta Gazette - Galley Proofs. (Box 13)
- Marietta Gazette - Letters to the Editor. (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Marietta Gazette - Orders for Printing Paper. (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Memorandum Book (Copyright Library), 1859-1868. (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Militia Papers. (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Miscellaneous. (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Music Book. (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Newspapers. (Map-case 2, Drawer 13)
- Notes and Incidents of the Life of John McDaniel. (Box 13)
- Orations, 1803-1806. (Box 7, Folder 7-12)
- Orations, n.d.. (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Playbill. (Box 13)
- Plats and Surveys. (Box 13)
- Poetry. (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Powers of Attorney/Proxies. (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Programs. (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Promissory Notes. (Box 7, Folder 17)
- Recipes. (Box 7, Folder 18)
- Report on the Commercial Relations of the U.S. With All Foreign Nations - Review. (Box 7, Folder 19)
- Resolution - Lincoln Lodge, 1816. (Box 7, Folder 20)
- Robey, Charles 0. - Store and Farm Accounts, 1856-1857. (Box 11)
- Ruy Blas!: Marie of Suabia or The Flower of the Rhine - A Play in Five Acts. (Box 7, Folder 21-22)
- Schedule (Inventory) of Furniture, 1864-1865. (Box 8, Folder 1)
- School Exercises. (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Scrapbook (Clippings), 1835-1837. (Box 13)
- Scrapbook (Clippings), 1871-1883. (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Scrapbook (Clippings) - Farm and Gardening Topics. (Box 12)
- Scrapbook (Clippings) - Financial and Commercial Topics, 1860-1861. (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Scrapbook (Clippings) - Foreign Items - North Italy, 1859. (Box 14)
- Scrapbook (Clippings) - Household and Cooking Topics. (Box 12)
- Scrapbook (Clippings) - Northern Pacific Railroad/Jay Cooke & Co. (Box 11)
- Scrapbook (Clippings) - Notices and Reviews of Books and Plays by Flagg, 1852-1858. (Box 12)
- Scrapbook (Clippings) - Venice, 1859-1861. (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Shipmaster's Ledger (Capt. Spencer Tinkham) and Daybook (Legal Fees), 1800, 1811-1814. (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Sketches of a Traveller. (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Speech, 1812(?). (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Speech Notes, 1812. (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Stock Transfers, 1814-1815. (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Suit Papers. (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Toast. (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Transmittal Certificate, 1850. (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Venice - Notes, etc. (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Venice - Notes, etc. (Box 13)
- Venice: The City of the Sea From the Invasion of Napoleon in 1797 to the Capitulation of Radetzky in 1849 - Abstracts, Extracts, etc. (Box 9, Folder 2-4)
- Venice: The City of the Sea From the Invasion of Napoleon in 1797 to the Capitulation of Radetzky in 1849 - Correspondence. (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Venice: The City of the Sea From the Invasion of Napoleon in 1797 to the Capitulation of Radetzky in 1849 - Part II - Manuscript Draft. (Box 9, Folder 6-13)
- Venice: The City of the Sea From the Invasion of Napoleon in 1797 to the Capitulation of Radetzky in 1849 - Part II - Manuscript Draft. (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
- Venice: The City of the Sea From the Invasion of Napoleon in 1797 to the Capitulation of Radetzky in 1849 - Part II - Manuscript Draft (2nd Version). (Box 10, Folder 3-4)
- Venice: The City of the Sea From the Invasion of Napoleon in 1797 to the Capitulation of Radetzky in 1849 - Notes. (Box 10, Folder 5-6)
- Will and Codocil of Edmund Flagg, 1810, 1815. (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Will of Nathaniel Teleson. (Box 10, Folder 8)